<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author>Jürgen Jakobitsch</author>
        <title>SemaGrow-Stack-Assembly - Building</title>
    </properties>
    <meta name="keyword" content="semagrow, build"/>
    <body>
        <section name="Building">
            <p>   
                This page contains information on how to create and customize debian/rpm
                distributions of the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Notes</li>
                    <li>System requirements</li>
                    <li>Build Lifecycle bindings</li>                    
                    <li>Creating a Debian package</li>
                    <li>Creating an RPM package</li>
                    <li>Generating the maven-site documentation</li>
                    <li>Customizing a local installation using build properties</li>                    
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>   
        <section name="Notes">
            <ul>
                <li>The following build instructions and customizations are for development only.</li>                
            </ul>
        </section>     
        <section name="System requirements">
            To be able to build the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp it is necessary that the following
            components are installed.
            <ol>
                <li>git<br/>
                    git is necessary to clone all repositories. All builds have been tested with
                    git version 1.8.1.4. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    git --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>JDK<br/>
                    A JDK (Java Development Kit) is necessary to compile all java-components. All builds
                    have been tested with java version 1.6.0_39. Please note that a JRE is not sufficient.
                    To check the installed version enter the following command in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    java -version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>Maven<br/>
                    Maven is necessary to build and assemble all components. All builds have
                    been tested with Apache Maven 3.0.3. Please make sure that mvn also uses the runtime
                    from the JDK and not from JRE. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    mvn --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>Debian Repository<br/>
                    The debian assembly deploys the finished deb-package to a given debian (apt) repository.
                    To get this build to work it is necessary to create a debian repository beforehand.
                    Please follow <a href="http://joseph.ruscio.org/blog/2010/08/19/setting-up-an-apt-repository/" target="_blank">this</a> guide to create one.
                    Please note that reprepro is used to deploy to the debian repository. It must be installed before
                    using the debian assembly.
                </li>
                <li>RPM Repository<br/>
                    The rpm assembly deploys the finished rpm-package to a given rpm repository.
                    To get this build to work it is necessary to create a rpm repository beforehand.
                    TODO : add info on rpm repository creation.
                </li>                
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Build Lifecycle bindings">
            <ol>
                <li>package
                    <ol>
                        <li>validate
                            <ol>
                                <li>Read build.properties file</li>
                                <li>Download SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp distribution zip and unpack it to copied-tomcat</li>
                            </ol>                        
                        </li>
                        <li>initialize
                            <ol>
                                <li>copy src/deb (src/rpm) files to target/deb (target/rpm)</li>
                                <li>copy src/script/* files to target</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>package
                            <ol>
                                <li>create debian/rpm packages</li>                                
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <li>deploy
                    <ol>
                        <li>validate
                            <ol>
                                <li>Read build.properties file</li>
                                <li>Download SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp distribution zip and unpack it to copied-tomcat</li>
                            </ol>                        
                        </li>
                        <li>initialize
                            <ol>
                                <li>copy src/deb (src/rpm) files to target/deb (target/rpm)</li>
                                <li>copy src/script/* files to target</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>package
                            <ol>
                                <li>create debian/rpm packages</li>                                
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>deploy
                            <ol>
                                <li>mark deploy scripts as executable</li>
                                <li>deploy debian/rpm packages to their respective repositories using provided deploy scripts</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>                        
                    </ol>
                </li>                
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Creating a Debian package">
            To create the SemaGrow-Stack's debian package simply cd into ${semagrow-stack-assembly.root}
            and issue the following command
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn clean package -P debian
</source>
            <br/>
            This will result in a deployable debian package in ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root}/target.
            This package can be used to install the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp. Please note that the 
            debian package can be used to directly install the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp or can be deployed
            to any debian repository.<br/>
            To use the deploy-debian script cd into ${semagrow-stack-assembly.root} and issue the following command<br/>
<source>
    mvn clean deploy -P debian
</source>          
            This will also run the deploy-debian script (/src/script/deploy-debian.sh). 
            The path of the debian repository is adjustable via the distribution.deb.repository setting
            in build.properties, see below on how to customize.
        </section>
        
        <section name="Creating an RPM package">
            To create the SemaGrow-Stack's RPM package simply cd into ${semagrow-stack-assembly.root}
            and issue the following command
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn clean package -P rpm
</source>
            <br/>
            This will result in a deployable RPM package in ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root}/target.
            This package can be used to install the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp. Please note that the 
            RPM package can be used to directly install the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp or can be deployed
            to any RPM repository.<br/>
            To use the deploy-rpm script cd into ${semagrow-stack-assembly.root} and issue the following command<br/>
<source>
    mvn clean deploy -P rpm
</source>          
            This will also run the deploy-debian script (/src/script/deploy-rpm.sh). 
            The path of the rpm repository is adjustable via the distribution.rpm.repository setting
            in build.properties, see below on how to customize.
        </section>

        <section name="Generating the maven-site documentation">
            SemaGrow-Stack-Assembly includes an automatically generated documentation including of
            dependency and license reports as well as javadoc and highlighted source code.
            To preview the generated documentation issue the following command in a terminal
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn site:run -P semagrow-stack-assembly-documentation
</source>
            <br/>
            This will run the documentation page on a local jetty at port 8080. The documentation
            page will be accessible via http://localhost:8080. Please note that normal site deployment
            is determined by the settings in pom.xml, see below.
        </section>        
        <section name="Customizing a local installation using build properties">
            SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp uses three property files with properties that can be overriden.
            <ul>
                <li>build.properties<br/>
                General build properties.                    
                </li>                
            </ul>
            <subsection name="build.properties">
                <ul>
                    <li>distribution.deb.repository<br/>
                    This setting determines the path to the debian repository when using the deploy goal.
                    </li>
                    <li>distribution.rpm.repository<br/>
                    This setting determines the path to the RPM repository when using the deploy goal.
                    </li>                    
                </ul>
            </subsection>            
            <subsection name="Overriding property files">
                To override above property files create an own properties file (either the build or the tomcat) 
                outside of ${semagrow-stack-assembly.root} and let maven use these properties instead
                of the default ones.
                To do so a settings.xml must be created, if it doesn't already exist, in the local maven repository
                which is usually in ~/.m2 (= /home/${username}/.m2 .
                see <a href="http://maven.apache.org/settings.html" target="_blank">here</a> for an empty settings.xml template.
                In the profiles section of the settings.xml create a new profile for the semagrow-stack-assembly build environment
                and mark it as active in the activeProfiles section.
<source>
    &lt;profiles&gt;
        &lt;profile&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;semagrow-stack-assembly&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;properties&gt;
                &lt;build.properties>/path/to/custom/build.properties&lt;/build.properties&gt;
            &lt;/properties&gt;
        &lt;/profile&gt;
    &lt;/profiles&gt;
    &lt;activeProfiles&gt;
        &lt;activeProfile&gt;semagrow-stack-assembly&lt;/activeProfile&gt;
    &lt;/activeProfiles&gt;
</source>
            </subsection>  
            <subsection name="Overriding distribution properties">
                To change the maven distribution (site distribution) target of a local installation either add the property distribution.mvn 
                (distribution.site) to an active profile in a local settings.xml (see above) or start the build with another system parameter
                using the -D option, for example
<source>
  mvn clean deploy -P debian -Ddistribution.mvn=/path/to/some/maven/repo
</source>                                
            This will copy the jar file along with the distribution debian file to the given maven repo.
<source>
  mvn clean site-deploy -P semagrow-stack-assembly-documentation -Ddistribution.site=/path/to/some/maven/site
</source>                                
            This will install the documentation files to the given maven directory.
            </subsection>              
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
